Nanae Momiyama
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Nanae Momiyama papers,
1928-circa 2000, bulk 1948-1990s
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Nanae Momiyama
3.0 linear feet
The papers of New York painter, calligrapher, and educator, Nanae Momiyama measure 3.0 linear feet and date from 1928-circa 2000, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1948-1990s. The collection traces Momiyama's career as a first wave post-World War II Japanese-American artist through biographical material, correspondence, writings and notes, business records, printed material, scrapbooks, sketches and sketchbooks, and photographs.
Provenance
The collection was donated by Haniwa Gottlieb, Nanae Momiyama's daughter, in 2009.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Nanae Momiyama (1924-2002) worked in New York and Greenwich, Connecticut as a painter, calligrapher, and educator.
In 1924, Nanae Momiyama was born in Tokyo, Japan. In 1944, she graduated from Bunka Gakuin College in Tokyo, where she later taught painting and drawing. In 1954, under the sponsorship of the Japanese government, Nanae Moimiyama attended the Art Students' League in New York City, where she was mentored by the painter, Morris Kantor. During this period, Momiyama participated in exhibitions organized by the cooperative galleries on East Tenth Street in New York City that were promoting the works of Abstract Expressionist artists.
Nanae Momiyama's artistic interests extended to the teaching of Japanese calligraphy and Sumi-e paintings at colleges, universities, and art institutions, including the National Teacher's Convention for Asian Studies at Brooklyn College, Columbia University, and Japan Society. During her career, Momiyama received commissions to design posters for movies, plays, and concerts and to illustrate books and magazines. In addition, she wrote Sumi-e, An Introduction to Ink Painting that became a standard text on the subject.
Nanae Momiyama participated in many solo and group exhibitions in the United States and abroad: Brata Gallery, the Bruce Museum, Gima Gallery, Ligoa Duncan Gallery, and Seibu Galleries, among others.
Nanae Momiyama was a long time resident of Greenwich, Connecticut. She died in 2002.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York painter, calligrapher, and educator, Nanae Momiyama measure 3.0 linear feet and date from 1928-circa 2000, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1948-1990s. The collection traces Momiyama's career as a first wave post-World War II Japanese-American artist through biographical material, correspondence, writings and notes, business records, printed material, scrapbooks, sketches and sketchbooks, and photographs.
Biographical material includes resumes, a graduation certificate, passports, artist's statements, a calendar of lectures, address books, miscellaneous biographical material, and a 1972 WGCH radio interview with Nanae Momiyama.
Correspondence is mostly professional and consists of incoming and outgoing letters with arts organizations, museums, and galleries, such as the Bruce Museum, the Japanese Artists'Association, Kenkeleba House, and the National Association of Women Artists. There is some personal correspondence from family and friends, including Yayoi Kusama and Johanna Secor.
Writings and notes contain writings and notes by Nanae Momiyama and others. Writings and notes mostly consist of drafts of lectures and press releases relating to Momiyama's class demonstrations on Sumi-e painting.
Business records include annotated painting lists, consignments, a loan agreement, a contract, and scattered receipts. Painting lists and sales receipts provide a detailed record of works sold by Nanae Momiyama from 1974-1987.
Nanae Momiyama's activities as an artist are well-documented through printed materials, including press releases, clippings, periodicals, exhibition invitations, announcements, and catalogs, periodicals, annotated checklists, and brochures. Also found is Momiyama's monograph on Sumi-e painting.
Five scrapbooks contain exhibition-related material, such as announcements, invitations, brochures, reviews, installation shots, and artwork. One scrapbook is of a more personal nature and includes notes, handmade holiday cards by the artist, and photographs of Momiyama's children.
Artwork comprises sketches, drawings, and graphic designs. Sketches are mostly studies for Nanae Momiyama's paintings. Also included are five sketchbooks; one sketchbook is devoted to Momiyama's calligraphy.
Photographs are of Nanae Momiyama and others, exhibition installations and artwork, miscellaneous photographs, and slides of artwork. Also found are six photograph albums of images of Nanae Momiyama with family, friends, and colleagues. Of interest, are two photograph albums depicting Nanae Momiyama's school life and social activities in Japan from 1928-1940s.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1948-1995 (Box 1: 0.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1953, 1970s-1993 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1950s-1995 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 4: Business Records, 1962-1987 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1950s-1995 (Box 1; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1948-1978 (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Sketches and Drawings, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 8: Sketchbooks, circa 1975-1997 (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 9: Photographs, 1928-circa 2000 (Box 3; 1.0 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Calligraphers; Calligraphy, Japanese; Educators--New York (State)--New York; Japanese American artists; Women painters--New York (State)--New York
Subjects-Geographical:
Japan
Types of Materials:
Drawings; Greeting cards; Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings
Names:
Kusama, Yayoi, 1929-; Secor, Johanna; Bruce Museum; Kenkeleba House; National Association of Women Artists (U.S.)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1948-1995, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
  Numerous versions of Nanae Momiyama's revised and edited resumes provide an overview of her professional activities over a thirty year period. This series includes some awards and prizes received by Nanae Momiyama, including the Twenty-third Grand Prix International de Peinture; the Grand Prix Humanitaire de France, Musee d'Art Modern de Ville de Paris; and the Gold Medal from the Accademia Italia.
  Files are arranged by subject and thereafter in chronological order.
  - Resumes, circa 1970s-1990s, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Graduation Certificate, Bunka Gakuin College of Fine Arts, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Passports, 1953-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Admission to International House, undated, 1948-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Artist's Statements, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Calendar of Lectures and Interviews, 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Awards, 1972-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memberships,undated, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Address Books, undated, circa 1970s-1975, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Interview with Nanae Momiyama, 1972-1973, (2 sound tape reels) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, 1954, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1953, 1970s-1993, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  Correspondence includes letters, drafts, postcards, and greeting cards. Letters reference Nanae Momiyama's participation in various arts organizations, the scheduling of exhibitions and lecture demonstrations, as well as her commissioned projects. Much of the correspondence is in Japanese.
  Files are arranged in chronological order.
  - Correspondence, undated, 1953, 1970s-1993, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-19)
  - Unidentified Correspondents, undated, 1959-1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Loose Envelopes,undated, 1963-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1950s-1995, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  This series includes writings and notes by Nanae Momiyama and by others. Included are Nanae Momiyama's drafts of her class presentations on calligraphy and Sumi-e painting.
  The article on Nanae Momiyama's work by art critic Alfred Werner is unpublished.
  Files are arranged by subject and thereafter filed in chronological order.
  - Typescripts of Presentations, circa 1950s-1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Press Releases, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Research Notes, circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes, undated, circa 1960s-1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Drafts of Article on Nanae Momiyama's artwork, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Business Records, 1962-1987, Series 4:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  Business records include annotated painting lists. Found is Nanae Momiyama's agreement to promote a Yves Saint Laurent fragrance for Charles of the Ritz, Ltd. as part of the company's marketing campaign.
  Files are arranged by subject and then chronologically.
  - Painting Lists, undated, 1974-1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Consignments and Loan Agreement, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Contract with Charles of the Ritz Group, Ltd., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Scattered Receipts, undated, 1962-1983, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
- Printed Material, circa 1950s-1995, Series 5:; (Box 1; 0.8 linear feet)
  Clippings, exhibition invitations, announcements, and catalogs trace Nanae Momiyama's exhibition history from the 1950s-1990s. There are a number of clippings from Japanese-American newspapers. Some checklists are annotated.
  Printed material can also be found in Series 6: Scrapbooks.
  Files are arranged by record type and filed thereafter in chronological order.
  - Press Releases, undated, 1958-1993 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Clippings About Nanae Momiyama, 1958-1995, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 33-38)
  - Clippings, General, undated, 1956-1987 (Folder 39)
  - Unidentified Clippings in Japanese, circa 1950s-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Periodicals, undated, 1953-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Invitations, undated, 1953-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Announcements, undated, circa 1956-1995, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, undated, 1952-1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Checklists, 1970-1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Brochures, undated, 1953-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, undated, circa 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated, circa 1950s-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Monograph, Sumi-E: An Introduction to Ink Painting, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Scrapbooks, 1948-1978, Series 6:; (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
  There are five scrapbooks. Four scrapbooks were received disbound and the pages are brittle. Volume 5 includes notes, handmade holiday cards by the artist, and photographs of Momiyama's children, and miscellaneous items.
  Scrapbooks are arranged in chronological order.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1948-1953, (1 vol. disbound) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook 2,1950s, (1 vol. disbound) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook 3,1953, (1 vol. disbound) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1956-1977, (1 vol. disbound) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook 5,1962-1978, (1 vol. disbound) (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Sketches and Drawings, circa 1950s-1970s, Series 7:; (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
  Sketches are done in ink, watercolor, and charcoal on paper and board, depicting mainly landscapes, flowers, and objects from nature, such as small insects and birds. Sketches include studies and finished drawings. Sketches are generally undated. Also included are Momiyama's logo design that was used on her stationery and exhibition announcements.
  Sketches and Drawings can also be found in Series 9: Photographs.
  Sketches are arranged in chronological order.
  - Sketches and Drawings, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Sketches and Drawings, 1962-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Sketches and Drawings, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Graphic Design Sketches, undated, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Sketchbooks, circa 1975-1997, Series 8:; (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
  This series comprises 7 sketchbooks of sketches or studies done in ink, wash, and pencil. Three small sketchbooks contain mostly genre scenes and buildings.
  Vol. 5 contains drawings by the artist after she suffered a stroke; most of the drawings are head studies and a few drawings are annotated.
  Sketchbooks were arranged in chronological order.
  - Sketchbooks 1-3, circa 1975-1979, (3 vols.) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Sketchbook 4, undated, 1991, (1 vol.) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Sketchbook 5, "Nanae Momiyama, Post Stroke," 1997, (1 vol.) (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Photographs, 1928-circa 2000, Series 9:; (Box 3; 1.0 linear feet)
  Most of the individuals and venues in photographs are unidentified. Included are photographs of Nanae Momiyama, wearing a traditional kimono and holding a Japanese calligraphic brush that were used for publicity purposes.
  Included are six photograph albums; three albums were received disbound. Interspersed among the pages of the volumes 1 and 2 are sketches by Nanae Momiyama and loose photographs. Photograph albums also contain personal snapshots and photographs of Momiyama's paintings.
  Photographs are arranged by subject and arranged in chronological order thereafter.
  The series is arranged as 5 subseries:
  9.1: Photographs of Nanae Momiyama and Others, 1928-circa 2000
  9.2: Exhibition Installations and Artwork, 1959-circa 1995
  9.3: Miscellaneous Photographs, 1983
  9.4: Slides of Artwork, 1975-1995
  9.5: Photograph Albums, 1938-circa 1990s
  - Photographs of Nanae Momiyama and Others, 1928-circa 2000, 9.1:
    - Nanae Momiyama,1940s-circa 2000, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Nanae Momiyama with Family, Friends, and Colleagues,1928-1990s, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - Family, Friends, and Colleagues, circa 1940s-1980s, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Photographs of Exhibition Installations and Artwork, 1959-circa 1995, 9.2:
    - Exhibition Installations, undated, 1959-1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Artwork,undated, 1972-circa 1995, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 8-11)
    - Transparencies, undated, 1968-1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, circa 1980s-1983, 9.3:
    - Nanae Momiyama Residence, Rye Brook, New York, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified Buildings, undated, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Slides of Artwork, 1975-1995, 9.4:
    - Slides of Artwork, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Slides of Artwork, 1978-1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Slides of Artwork, 1981-1987, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photograph Albums, 1938-circa 1990s, 9.5:
    - Vol. 1: Nanae Momiyama with Family and Friends, circa 1938-1940 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Vol. 2: Nanae Momiyama with Family and Friends, undated, 1938-1943 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Vol. 3: Nanae Momiyama with Family, Friends, and Colleagues,circa 1958-1970s, (1 vol. disbound) (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Vol. 4: Nanae Momiyama with Family,circa 1970s-1980s, (1 vol. disbound) (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Vol. 5: Nanae Momiyama with Colleagues and Students, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Vol. 6: Artwork, circa 1979, (1 vol. disbound) (Box 3, Folder 23)